<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short account of the process and trial at the instance of His Majesty's advocate by special order of His Majesty's privy council against Thomas Frazer of Beaufort and Captain Simeon Frazer his son and their complices for the crimes of treason and other crimes contained in their inditement.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B10030</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3543A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217944</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">62369671</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 62369671</idno>
            <idno type="VID">188134</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B10030)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 188134)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2856:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short account of the process and trial at the instance of His Majesty's advocate by special order of His Majesty's privy council against Thomas Frazer of Beaufort and Captain Simeon Frazer his son and their complices for the crimes of treason and other crimes contained in their inditement.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>17 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fraser, Thomas, 1631-1699</term>
               <term>Lovat, Simon Fraser, --  Lord, 1667?-1747.</term>
               <term>Trials (Treason) --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702 --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1689-1702 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:188134:1"/>
            <head>A ſhort Account of the Proceſs and Trial at the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of His Majeſty's Advocat, by ſpecial Order of His Majeſty's Privy Council, againſt <hi>Thomas Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer</hi> of <hi>Beaufort,</hi> and Captain
<hi>Simeon. Frazer</hi> his Son, and their Complices, for the Crimes of Treaſon, and other Crimes contained in their Inditement.</head>
            <p>LOrd <hi>Lovat</hi> having deceaſed in the year 1696, leaving four Daughters under age, in the keeping and cuſtody of their Mother; and the Right of Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, according to the Tenor of the Lord <hi>Lovat</hi>'s Infeftments, as well as by his own expreſs Deeds, divolving upon the eldeſt Daughter: Nevertheleſs <hi>Thomas Fraſer</hi> of <hi>Beaufort,</hi> and Captain <hi>Simeon Fraſer</hi> his Son, pretending, That they were the apparent Heirs Male of the Family, and alledging (without any ground) that the Right of Succeſſion of the Eſtate of <hi>Lovat</hi> ſhould only appertain to them; endeavour to Poſſeſs thoſe of the Name, and the Vaſſals and dependers on the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, (who make a numerous Clan in the
<hi>Highland</hi> parts) That the young La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy the Heireſs was to be diſpoſed upon by her Mother and Friends, to a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and that thereby their <hi>Clan</hi> and <hi>Chiftainrie</hi> (Names of great Value, with that ſort of people) were to be broken, and they brought under Subjection to a Foreign Lord and Maſter.</p>
            <p>Whereupon the ſaid <hi>Thomas Fraſer,</hi> with his Son
<hi>Simeon Fraſer,</hi> (tho Perſons of no Eſtate, and who for a long time had lived precariouſly by the allowance and tollerance of the Lord
<hi>Lovat,</hi> upon a piece of Land of his called <hi>Beaufort</hi>) do enter into a Combination and Conſpiracy with thoſe of the Name of
<hi>Faſer,</hi> whom they could induce to follow them; and firſt, holding ſecret Councils, and ſigning Bonds and Leagues amongſt themſelves, and then making open Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations and Rendevouzes in Arms, they reſolve about the Month of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> 1697, to invade and poſſeſs the Eſtate and Lordſhip of <hi>Lovat</hi> (to which they knew perfectly that they had no legal Right or Title) by plain Force and Violence. And thus proceeding from one Step and Degree of Violence to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they break out into a treaſonable riſing in Arms, and open and manifeſt Rebellion againſt his Majeſty. And that attended with the Aggravations of ſuch inſolent and horrid Crimes, as have ſcarce been heard of in any Civil Nation or Kingdom.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the exact account of theſe their Crimes and Treaſons, as alſo of the Method taken by the Lords of his Majeſty's Privy Council to reduce them to a better Mind, and prevent the foreſaid Extreamities, will beſt appear from the two libels or Inditements, which upon t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> occaſion are raiſed againſt them; the juſt and full doubles thereof were and are as follows.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:188134:2"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="indictment">
                        <head>The juſt double of the firſt Libel or Inditement exhibit and inſiſted upon, by his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty's Advocat, before the Lords of her Majeſties Juſticiary at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> the 5th. day of
<hi>September</hi> 1698, Againſt <hi>Thomas Fraſer</hi> of
<hi>Beaufort,</hi> and Captain <hi>Simon Fraſer</hi> his Son, and their Accomplices afternamed.</head>
                        <p>THat where, by the Laws of this, and all other well governed Nations, the Crimes of Treaſon and Rebellion; As likewiſe of unlawful Leagues and Combinations, and the convocating and conveening of Subjects in Arms, without the warrand of Authority, and the ocupying, poſſeſſing, ſtuffing, and fortifying of Houſes and Forts, with armed Men, and other Proviſions: As alſo, the way-laying, Seiſing, Apprehending, and making free Subjects Priſoners, and detaining them <hi>in privato carcere,</hi> or in Bondage and Captivity, and treating them with Inſolence and Cruelty: As likewiſe, the raviſhing or offering to Raviſh Women by Force and Violence, and without Reſpect to the Quality or Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Perſons injured, or even to common Humanity; and the perſiſting in the ſaid Violence, Rapt, and Raviſhing, by carrying the Raviſhed about from Place to Place, at the pleaſure of the Raviſher, are puniſhable with Confiſcation of Life, Lands, and Goods. Likeas, by the Act of Parliament King
<hi>James</hi> 1ſt. Par. 1ſt. Cap. 3d. It is ſtatute, That no man openly Rebel againſt us, under the pain of Forfeiture of Life and Goods. And by the Act of Parliament <hi>James</hi> the 2d. <hi>Parl.</hi> 6. <hi>Cap.</hi> 24. It is ſtatute, That who commits Treaſon againſt Our Perſon and Majeſty, riſes in feir of War againſt Us, Reſets and ſupplies ſuch as have commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Treaſon, or ſtuffs their Houſes, and holds them againſt us, or ſtuffs Houſes of their own, in furtherance of Rebels, ſhall be puniſhed as Traitors. And by the Act of Parliament Queen <hi>Mary, Par.</hi>
9. <hi>Cap.</hi> 75. It is ſtatute, That none attempt to do, or riſe any Bands of Men of War, on Horſe or Foot, with Culverings, Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtols, Picks, Spears, or other Munition bellical, without ſpecial Licenſe in writ of our Sovereign Lady, and her Succeſſors, under the pain of Death, to be execute upon the raiſers of the ſaid Bands. As alſo upon them that raiſes and conveens in the Bands. And by the Act, <hi>James</hi> 6th <hi>Parl.</hi> 8th.
<hi>Cap.</hi> 131. It is ſtatute, That none of our Subjects preſume to convocat, conveen, or aſſemble, for holding of Councils to treat, conſult, or determin in any matter of State, Civil or Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtick, except in the ordinary Judgement, without our ſpecial Command, or expreſs Licence, under the pain made againſt ſuch as unlawfully convocats our Leidges. And by another Act <hi>James</hi> 6th. <hi>Parl.</hi> 10th.
<hi>Chap.</hi> 12. It is ſtatute, That no Leagues or Bands be made againſt our Subjects, of any Degree, without Privity and conſent, under the pain to be holden and execute as movers of Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to the breach of the peace: Which two laſt Act are ratified by <hi>Charles</hi> 2d. <hi>Parl.</hi> 1ſt.
<hi>Cap.</hi> 4th. And by the Act <hi>Charles</hi> 2d. <hi>Par.</hi> 1.
<hi>Chp.</hi> 5th. It is declared, That it is, and ſhall be high Treaſon to the Subjects of this Kingdom. or any number of them, more or leſs, upon any Ground or pretext whatſoever, to riſe and continue in Arms, to maintain any Forts, Strength, or Gariſons, or to make any Treaties or leagues with Forreigners, or amongſt themſelves, without our ſpecial Authority and Approbation, firſt had, and obtained thereto. And by the Act <hi>Charles</hi>
2d. <hi>Par.</hi> 1ſt. <hi>Seſſion</hi> 2d. <hi>cap.</hi> 2d. It is ſtatute and declared, That to plot, contrive, or intend to levie War, or to take up Arms againſt us, or any commiſſionat by us, is puniſhable as high Treaſon. Likeas, by the Act <hi>Charles</hi> 2d. <hi>parl,</hi> 2d.
<hi>Cap.</hi> 11th. It is ſtatute, That in time coming, in all caſes of Treaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able riſing in Arms, and open, and manifeſt Rebellion againſt us and our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, our Advocat for the time, may and ought to inſiſt againſt, and proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute<pb n="3" facs="tcp:188134:2"/>ſuch perſons as he ſhall be ordered by us, or our privy Council to Purſue: And if they be Cited and do not compear, the Judges (notwithſtanding of their abſence) may and ought to proceed to conſider, and give Interlocutor upon the Libel; and if it be found Relevant, admit the ſame to the knowledge of an Aſſiſe, and upon their Verdict, find the ſame to be proven, The Doom and Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Forfeiture ought to proceed, and be given in the ſame manner, as if the perſons accuſed had compeared, and were preſent. Which raiſing Convocatting and Conveening in Arms without or againſt our Authority, which the other Crimes foreſaid are highly aggravated, and the Treaſon and Rebellion yet more open and manifeſt, while the perſons guilty preſume to perſiſt and continue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, after having been charged in our Name, by our Officers, or by a Herauld thereto Waranted, to lay down their Arms, and render their perſons to bide the Law; under the pain of Rebellion. As alſo, by the 34th Act Parliament 1ſt. Seſſ. 1ſt. <hi>Ch.</hi> 2d. It is ſtatute, That the celebrater of Clandeſtine Marriages be baniſhed the Kingdom, never to return under the pain of Death. <hi>NEVER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THELEES,</hi> It is of verity, That Captain <hi>Simon Fraſer,</hi> Eldeſt lawful Son to <hi>Thomas Fraſer</hi> of <hi>Beaufort, William Fraſer</hi> of <hi>Foger, Hugh Fraſer</hi> in <hi>K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>nmonavie, William Fraſer</hi> in <hi>Dulleraig, William Fraſer</hi> of <hi>Erechit, Alexander Fraſer</hi> of <hi>Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duthill</hi> younger, <hi>Hugh Fraſer,</hi> alias <hi>Huiſton Oig</hi> in <hi>Leadclune, Alexander Fraſer</hi> in <hi>Ruthven, Jhon Fraſer</hi> his Brother, <hi>Alexander Fraſer</hi> Son to <hi>Farratin, Alexander Fraſor</hi> Son to <hi>Meggivie, Tais Fraſer</hi> Brother to <hi>Litlegarth, Thomas Huiſton</hi> Son to the Miniſter of <hi>Stratherick, Aeneas Macbaine</hi> Brother to <hi>Drummond Macbaine, Hugh Fraſer</hi> Son to <hi>Struie, Hugh Fraſer</hi> younger of
<hi>Boch rubine, John Fraſer</hi> Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Old <hi>Kilduthill,</hi> Major
<hi>Thomas Fraſer</hi> Elder of <hi>Struie, Hugeh Fraſer</hi> Brother to
<hi>Srechits,</hi> and <hi>John Fraſer</hi> younger of <hi>Meggive,</hi> Shaking off all fear of God and regard to our Laws and Authority, are guilty, airt and part of the Crimes above and under mentioned. In ſo far as, The ſaid Captain <hi>Simon Fraſer</hi> having on one or other of the days of the Month of <hi>September</hi> laſt ſent to the foreſaids perſons to come and meet him at <hi>Moniack,</hi> a Houſe belonging to <expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:leftblank"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>left blank</ex>
                           </expan>
                           <hi>Fraſer</hi> of <hi>Strichen,</hi> they agreed and came to the foreſaid Houſe, belonging to <hi>Strichen,</hi> and there then being ſeveral other Gentlemen of the Name of <hi>raſer</hi> and others; They unlawfully leagued and combined together for to riſe in Arms and proſecute their miſchievous Practices. Likeas, for their better effectuating thereof, Intimation having been made by one or other of the Perſons above-mentioned to the Men of
<hi>Stratherick,</hi> (which is a part of the Lord <hi>Lovats</hi> Eſtate and Intereſt,) They within three or four days after the meeting at
<hi>Strichens</hi> Houſe, did rendezvous about two hundred Men in Arms at
<hi>Eſseck.</hi> And when the Men of <hi>Stratherick,</hi> did come to the ſaid Rendezvous at <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> about two hundred Men in Arms, as ſaid is, the ſaid <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Simon Fraſers</hi> of
<hi>Beaufort,</hi> and the other Perſons above-complained upon, did encourage theſe Men, unlaufully conveened in Arms, as ſaid is, by ſwearing, and cauſing them ſwear to join and concur for maintaining the ſaids
<hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Simon Fraſer</hi>'s Pretences to the Eſtate of
<hi>Lovat,</hi> againſt all Oppoſers. Likeas after the Rendezvous, the ſaid <hi>Thomas and Simon Fraſers,</hi> and others above complain'd upon, that had been at the Rendezvous, went into a Change-Houſe near by, and there contriv'd and drew up the Letter ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by them, directed to the Lord
<hi>Fraſer:</hi> And of which Letter a Copy is hereto ſubjoyn'd (the principle being put in the Clerk of Juſticiaries hands) and doth manifeſtly contain an unlawful League and Combination, for mutual Adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in their wicked Deſigns, which League and Combination is the rather ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravated than paliated by any exeception therein of the King and Government, as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:188134:3"/>being <hi>proteſtatio contrario facto.</hi> Likeas, the ſaid Letter of Aſſociation doth alſo contain bold and wicked Threatnings againſt the Lord <hi>Saltoun,</hi> and falſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due Reflections and Inſinuations againſt the Marqueſs of <hi>Athol</hi> and his Family. And this Letter being framed, and agreed to as ſaid is, to be ſent to the Lord <hi>Fraſer,</hi> after his parting from the Banders and Leaguers, doth further declared their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to continue in the ſaid unlawful Aſſociation, and to have the ſame recorded <hi>ad futuram rei memoriam.</hi> And the Letter was accordingly ſent to the Lord
<hi>Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer,</hi> to his Houſe of <expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:leftblank"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>left blank</ex>
                           </expan> The Lord <hi>Saltoun</hi> having gone North the next day, to viſit the Lady <hi>Dowager</hi> of
<hi>Lovat</hi> at her Houſe of <hi>Caſtledounie,</hi> after he had ſtay'd there a few days, and as he was returning homeward with the Lord <hi>Mungo Murray,</hi> Son to the Marqueſs of <hi>Athol,</hi> and ſome other Gentlemen, by the way paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing throw the Wood of <hi>Bonchrew,</hi> about four Miles from <hi>Caſtledounie,</hi> the ſaid Lord <hi>Saltoun,</hi> Lord
<hi>Mungo Murray,</hi> and their Company, were upon the ſixth, or one or other of the days of <hi>October</hi> laſt, ſurpriſed by the ſaid Captain <hi>Simon Fraſer</hi> and his Father, who having convocat a great many Men in Arms, above fourſcore, or a hundred, did place themſelves in ambuſh, for way-laying and ſeiſing the ſaid Lord <hi>Saltoun,</hi> Lord
<hi>Mungo Murray,</hi> and their Company. Whom they according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly s;eiſed with great Violence and Barbarity, Diſarming, Diſmounting, throwing them down, and Beating them, with many Threatnings, to Murther them out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right. And the ſaid <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Simon Fraſers</hi> having, with their foreſaid Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, (whereof ſeveral were Subſcribers of the foreſaid Letter of <hi>Aſſociation</hi>) taken Priſoners the Lord
<hi>Saltoun,</hi> Lord <hi>Mungo Murray,</hi> and their Company, unable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt ſo great a Force, they cauſed them to Mount on little pitiful Beaſts, inſtead of their own Horſes, whereof they had rob'd them as alſo of their Armr, and other things about them, and thus carried them away Captives, under their Guards of Men and Arms, to the Houſe of
<hi>Fanellan,</hi> where they made them cloſs Priſoners every one in a Room by himſelf, for the ſpace of ſix or ſeven days, having in the mean time fortified and ſtuffed the Houſe with Armed Men and other Proviſions. And further, in proſecution of their wicked Band and League to riſe in Arms, the ſaid <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Simon Fraſers,</hi> and their Complices, ſent the Firie Croſs through the Countrey, to raiſe their Men and People in Arms; whereby they conveened to the Number of two hundred Men in Arms, to aſſiſt and joyn with the ſaids <hi>Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers,</hi> and others above-complained upon, in their foreſaid open and manifeſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection and Rebellion: In further proſecuting whereof, the ſaid <hi>Thomas</hi> and
<hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Fraſers,</hi> and their Complices above-complained upon, did the ſame day that they made the Lord <hi>Saltoun,</hi> Lord <hi>Mungo Murray,</hi> and others their Priſoners, march with a Company of about one Hundred Men in Arms, to the Lady <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat</hi>'s Houſe of
<hi>Caſtledounie,</hi> and there, violently and wickedly ſeiſed upon the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow Lady and her Servants, and made them Priſoners; and robbed and ſpoiled the Goods in and about the Houſe, at their pleaſure. And thus the ſaid <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Simon Fraſers,</hi> and their Complices above complained upon, having broken out into open Rebellion and Arms, and ſeiſed the foreſaid two Houſes with the Priſoners therein, they gariſoned the ſame, and appointed Captains, and other Officers over their Troops and Gariſons: And adding yet more Barbarity to all their Violence, they ſet up a Gallows before the Houſe of <hi>Fanellan,</hi> and in the View of the Windows where the Priſoners were, threatning to hang them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And by ſending tee ſaid Firie Croſs as ſaid is, they convocat and conveened yet more Men in Arms, and after they had keeped the ſaids Priſoners, ſome ſix or ſeven days in the foreſaid Captivity and Terrors, they carried them from <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nellan</hi> by armed Guards, to the Iſle of <hi>Aigies,</hi> where they keeped them Priſoners<pb n="5" facs="tcp:188134:3"/>in a Creel Houſe for their Lodging, and did treat them in a moſt miſerable man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ſo that the Lord <hi>Saltoun</hi> fell ſo ſick, that they were obliged to diſmiſs him, but ſtill keeping the Lord <hi>Mungo Murray</hi> Priſoner for ſome days thereafter: And about the ſame time, they have the Lady
<hi>Dowager</hi> of <hi>Lovat</hi> ſtill their Priſoner in
<hi>Caſtledounie.</hi> And during their Impriſonment, the ſaid
<hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Simon Fraſers,</hi> and their Complices above-complain'd upon, propone Conditions, extort Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles and Agreements, and whatever they pleaſed to demand, there being no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting ſuch a wicked and barbarous Force, which continually proceeded to great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Violence and Barbarity. For not only the ſaid <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Simon Fraſers</hi> and their ſaid Complices, refuſed to lay down their Arms, and deſiſt from their Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, when commanded and charged by the Sheriff of <hi>Inverneſs;</hi> But going on in their Villainous Barbarities, they keeped the ſaid Lady <hi>Dowager,</hi> in moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Captivity. And when nothing that ſhe could propoſe or promiſe would ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie them, the ſaid Captain <hi>Simon</hi> takes up the moſt Mad and Villainous Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that ever was heard of: For all in a ſudden, he and his ſaids Complices makes the Lady cloſs Priſoner in her Chamber, under his armed Guards; And then comes upon her, with Mr. <hi>Robert Monro</hi> Miniſter at
<hi>Abertarſe,</hi> and three or four Ruffians in the Night time, about two or three in the Morning in the Month of <hi>October</hi> laſt, or one or other of the days of the ſaid Month of <hi>October</hi> laſt: And having drag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged out her Maids, <hi>Agnes Mackbrayer,</hi> and <expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:leftblank"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>left blank</ex>
                           </expan>
                           <hi>Fraſer,</hi> he propoſes to the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that ſhe ſhould Marry him. And when ſhe fell in Lamenting and Crying, the great Pipe was blown up, to drown her cryes, and the wicked Villains order the Miniſter to proceed. And tho ſhe proteſted with Tears and Cries, and alſo offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all promiſes of any thing elſe, and declared ſhe would ſacrifice her Life, ſooner then conſent to their Propoſal, nevertheleſs the ſaid Miniſter proceeds, and declares them Married Perſons: And <hi>Hugh Fraſer</hi> of
<hi>Kinmonavie,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Hutcheon Oig,</hi> (both of them Thieves and Murtherers) are appointed for her waiting Maids. And tho ſhe often ſwarfed and again cryed out moſt grievouſly, yet not relenting, but the Bag-pipe is blown up as formerly, and the foreſaid Ruffians rent off her Cloaths, cutting her Stays with their Durks, and ſo thruſt her into her Bed. After this moſt horrid violent Rapt, when the Ladies Friends offered to make ſome Attempt, for her Reſcue out of Captain <hi>Simon</hi>'s hands, the ſaid Captain <hi>Simon,</hi> and his ſaid Complices, carry her away to the Hills, and raiſing the Countrey, to the number of four or five hundred Men in Arms, of their own Name and Dependers, did detain ſtill the afflicted Lady, and did ſtand to their own Defence. And further, when the Lords of our Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, having Intelligence of this Violence and Inſurrection in Arms, and of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid wicked Practices and Rebellion of the ſaid
<hi>Fraſers,</hi> and others above complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned upon, did order an Herauld to charge the ſaid Traitors and Rebels, to lay down their Arms, and ſet the Lady at Liberty, and render themſelves Priſoners, to abide the Law: And did alſo order the Sheriff, with the <hi>Paſse Comitatus,</hi> as likewiſe our Troops and Forces to march againſt them, and ſubdue them. Yet the foreſaids <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>Simon Fraſers,</hi> and their ſaids Complices, diſobeyed the ſaid Charge, and in manifeſt Contempt thereof, continued in Arms and Rebellion for a conſiderable time after they were ſo charged, and detained the ſaid Lady Priſoner for ſeveral days thereafter. By all which it is evident, that the whole foreſaids Perſons, and each of them <hi>Reſpective,</hi> are guilty as Actors, at leaſt as airt and part, of the Crimes of Treaſon and open Rebellion, convocating and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veening in Arms, unlawful Banding and Leaguing, Robbery, Raviſhment, and the other Violences and Crimes above-mentioned, or of one or other of them. As alſo, the ſaid Mr. <hi>Robert Monro</hi> Miniſter, is guilty of celebrating a Clande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine<pb n="6" facs="tcp:188134:4"/>Marriage: Which being found by the Knowledge of an Inqueſt, they ought to be puniſhed by Confiſcation of Life, Lands, Honours, and Goods, and other pains of Law, to the Example and Terror of others to commit the like in time coming.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="indictment">
                        <head>Follows the juſt Double of the Second Lybel or Inditement againſt the <hi>Fraſers.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>THat where, by the Laws of this, and all other well governed Realms, the Crimes of Treaſon and Rebellion, and open Inſurrection in Arms, as likewiſe of unlawful Leagues and Combinations, and the Convocating or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veening of our Subjects in Arms, without the Warrand of our Authority, and the Occupying, Poſſeſſing, Stuffing, and Fortifying of Houſes, and Fortifying of Houſes and Forts with Armed Men, and other Proviſions: As alſo the way-lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſeiſing, apprehending, and making free Subjects Priſoners, and detaining them by Violence in Bondage and Captivity, and treating them with all hardſhips, are puniſhable with Confiſcation of Life, Lands and Goods: Likewiſe by the Act of Parliament,
<hi>Ja.</hi> 1ſt. <hi>Par.</hi> 1ſt. <hi>Cap.</hi> 3d. It is Statute, That no Man openly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel againſt us, under the Pain of Forfeiture of Life and Goods: And by the Act of Parliament <hi>Ja.</hi> 2d. <hi>Par.</hi> 6th.
<hi>Cap.</hi> 24th. It is Statute, That who commits Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon againſt our Perſon and Majeſty, riſes in Feir of War againſt us, reſets and ſupplies ſuch as have committed Treaſon, or Stuffs their Houſes and holds them againſt us, or Stuffs Houſes of their own in Furtherance of Rebels, ſhall be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed as Traitors. And by the Act of Parliament Queen
<hi>Mary, Par.</hi> 9th. <hi>Cap.</hi> 75. It is Statute, That none attempt to do or raiſe any Bands of Men of War, upon Horſe or Foot, with Culverings, Piſtols, Picks, Spears, or other Munition Belli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, without ſpecial Licenſe in Writ of her Majeſty and her Succeſſors, under the Pain of Death to be execute upon the Raiſers of the ſaids Bands, as alſo upon them that riſes and conveens in Bands. And by the Act, <hi>Ja.</hi> 6th.
<hi>Par.</hi> 8th. <hi>Cap.</hi> 131. It is Statute, That none of our Subjects preſume to Convocat, Conveen or Aſſemble for holding of Councils, to treat, conſult, or determine in any Matter of State, Civil or Eccleſiaſtick, except in the ordinary Judgements, without our ſpecial Command or expreſs Licenſe, under the Pains made againſt ſuch as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully Convocats our Leiges: And by another Act, <hi>Ja.</hi> 6th.
<hi>Par.</hi> 10th <hi>Cap.</hi> 12th It is Statute, That no Leagues or Bands be made amongſt our Subjects of any Degree, without our Privity and Conſent, under the Pain to be holden and execute as Movers of Sedition to the Breach of the Peace. Which two laſt Acts are ratified, <hi>Ch.</hi> 2d.
<hi>Par.</hi> 1ſt. <hi>Cap.</hi> 4th. And by the Act, <hi>Ch.</hi> 2d.
<hi>Par.</hi> 1ſt. <hi>Cap.</hi> 5. It is Declared, That it is, and ſhall be High Treaſon to the Subjects of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, or any number of them, more or leſs, upon any Ground or pretext what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, to riſe and continue in Arms, to maintain any Forts, ſtrengths or Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or to make any Treaties or Leagues with Forreigners, or amongſt themſelves, without our ſpecial Authority and Approbation firſt had and obtained thereto. And by the Act, <hi>Ch.</hi> 2d. <hi>Par.</hi> 1ſt. <hi>Seſ.</hi> 2d.
<hi>Cap.</hi> 2d. It is ſtatute and declared, That to plot, contrive, or intend to levy War, or to take up arms againſt us, or any Commiſſionat by us, is puniſhable as high Treaſon. Likeas, by the Act, <hi>Ch.</hi> 2d.
<hi>Par.</hi> 2d. <hi>Cap.</hi> 11th. It is ſtatute, That in time coming, in all Caſes of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable riſing in Arms, and open and manifeſt Rebellion againſt us and our Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, our Advocat for the time, may, and ought to inſiſt, and proſecute ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as he ſhall be ordered by us, and our Privy Council to purſue. And if they be cited, and do not appear, the Juſtices notwithſtanding of their Abſence, may,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:188134:4"/>and ought to proceed to conſider, and give Interlocutor upon the Libel: And if it be found relevant, admit the ſame to the knowledge of an Aſſize, and upon their Verdict, finding the ſame to be proven, the Doom and Sentence of Forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ought to proceed, and be given in the ſame manner, as if the Perſons accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed had compeared, and were preſent. Which raiſing, convocating, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veening in Arms, without, or againſt our Authority, with the other Crimes fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, are highly aggravated, and the Treaſon and Rebellion becomes yet more wicked and attrocious, when they are perpetrat by Perſons under Proceſs for for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Treaſons, and other capital and wicked Crimes, and after having been Charged in our Name by our Officers, or by a Herauld thereto warranted, to lay down their Arms, and render their Perſons to abide the Law, under the pain of Rebellion. Likeas, to attempt to ſeiſe, and actually ſeiſe, and keep back by force and Violence, Perſons cited, and under Bail, to appear before the Court of Juſticia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or any other Court or Judicature, to bear Witneſs, and give evidence, or for any other Cauſe or effect. As alſo, to extort by Force and Violence, Bonds, Declarations, or any other Write or Paper from any one of our free Leiges, are likewiſe Crimes of a high nature, and ought to be ſeverely puniſhed. NEVER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THELESS, it is of verity, That the ſaid <hi>Thomas</hi> and
<hi>Simon Fraſers,</hi> and the whole other perſons above complained upon, ſhaking off all fear of God, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to our Laws and Authority, are guilty, airt and part, of the Crimes above, and after mentioned. In ſo far as the ſaid Captain <hi>Simon Fraſer</hi> and his Complices above named, being either already under a Proceſs of Treaſon, or deſigning to fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the foreſaid Proceſs raiſed againſt others of their Accomplices, did upon the occaſion that certain perſons Witneſſes, were to come, or be brought from <hi>Strath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erick,</hi> and the bounds adjacent thereto, within the Shire of <hi>Inverneſs,</hi> for to give evidence in the ſaid Proceſs anent the Crimes of Treaſon, and others therein li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled, wickedly add to all their former Rebellions, and wicked horrid Crimes, their convocating and conveening in Arms of Men, to the Number of Two or Three hundred Men leſs or more; who appearing in an open Inſurrection, and manifeſt Rebellion in Arms, did upon the fifteenth of <hi>June</hi> laſt bypaſt, the ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth, ſeventeenth, and eighteenth, or one or orher of the days of the ſaid Month, March in feir of War, and open Hoſtility, againſt certain of our loyal Subjects, conveened by our Authority: And for furthering of Juſtice within the foreſaid bounds of <hi>Stratherick,</hi> and others within the Shire of <hi>Inverneſs,</hi> and their invading and incompaſſing, threatning and over-maſtering them, did ſeiſe upon their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and make them Priſoners, and violently keeped back ſuch as were either ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or under Bail, to appear and give Evidence and Witneſs in the Proceſs above-mentioned. As alſo, they extorted from our free Lieges, certain Bonds, Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and Writs, according to their own wicked Imaginations and Purpoſes: Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, that they might raiſe and promote their foreſaid manifeſt Inſurrection and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, they ſent the fiery Croſs through the Country (a ſign and ſymbol uſed amongſt them, to gather their Complices in Arms) for making Inſurrection and Rebellions, and other unlawful Convocations: As alſo, they did place a Gariſon in <hi>John Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers</hi> Houſe of <hi>Meiklegart</hi> in <hi>Stratherick,</hi> and in a word, have committed moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt Treaſon and Rebellion by open riſing in Arms againſt our Laws and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and uſing Hoſtilities and Violences upon our good Subjects. By all which it is manifeſt, That the foreſaids perſons complained upon, or one or other of them, are guilty of the Crimes of open and manifeſt Rebellion in Arms, Treaſon, unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Convocations, Violent Impriſonment, and the hail other Crimes above libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: Which being found by the knowledge of an Inqueſt, they ought to be<pb n="8" facs="tcp:188134:5"/>condignly puniſhed by the Forfeiture of Life, Lands, Honour, and Goods; to the Example and Terror of others to commit the like in time coming.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>This being the Libels and Inditements raiſed and purſued by his Majeſty's Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocat, againſt the forenamed Perſons, and the Criminal Letters, containing the ſame, with the Execution thereof by Purſevants and Heraulds, with Coats of Arms diſplayed, and ſound of Trumpet, and other Solemnities appointed by Act of Parliament, having been duely returned to the Clerk of the foreſaid Court of Juſticiary, at the Days and Diets thereof: His Majeſties Advocat, after the Court was fenced, and that he had firſt given in the Order and Warrand of the Lords of his Majeſty's Privy Council, for his purſuing of the foreſaid Proceſs of Treaſon, produced the criminal Letters of Treaſon duely execute; and the Purſevant who execute the Letters, with his Witneſſes being ſolemnly ſworn, and having made faith upon the Truth of the Executions, his Majeſty's Advocat declared, that the perſons ſummoned, againſt whom he intended to inſiſt, being abſent, and not compearing, to underly the Law, he did inſiſt againſt the perſons after named, in order to their Forfeiture in abſence,
<hi>viz.</hi> Captain <hi>Simon Fraſer,</hi> eldeſt lawful Son to
<hi>Thomas Fraſer</hi> of <hi>Beaufort, William Fraſer</hi> of <hi>Foyr, Hugh Fraſer</hi> in <hi>Kinmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>navie, William Fraſer</hi> in <hi>Dulleraig, William Fraſer</hi> of <hi>Erech it, Alexander Fraſer</hi> of
<hi>Kilduthil</hi> younger, <hi>Hugh Fraſer,</hi> alias <hi>Huiſton Oig</hi> in <hi>Leadclune, Alexander Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer</hi> in <hi>Ruthven, John Fraſer</hi> his Brother, <hi>Alexander Fraſer,</hi> Son to <hi>Farralin, Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander Fraſer</hi> Son to <hi>Meggivie, Tais Fraſer</hi> Brother to
<hi>Litlegarth, Thomas Huiſton</hi> Son to the Miniſter of <hi>Stratherick, Aeneas Mcbaine</hi> Brother to <hi>Drummond Mcbaine, Hugh Fraſer</hi> Son to
<hi>Struie, Hugh Fraſer</hi> younger of <hi>Bochrubine, John Fraſer,</hi> Brother to old <hi>Kilduthill,</hi> Major <hi>Thomas Fraſer</hi> Elder of
<hi>Struie, Hugh Fraſer,</hi> Brother to <hi>Erchit,</hi> and <hi>John Fraſer</hi> younger of <hi>Meggivie.</hi> Whereupon the Lords of Juſticiary, having with conſent of his Majeſty's Advocat, deſerted the Diet as to certain other perſons contained in the Inditement, and his Majeſty's Advocat, having reſtricted the Libels againſt Captain <hi>Simon Fraſer,</hi> and the other perſons inſiſted againſt, to their Treaſonable riſing in Arms, and open Rebellion againſt his Majeſty, in the terms of the Act of Parliament 1669, which in the caſe of theſe Crimes, allows and ordains Proceſs of Treaſon to proceed before the Lords of Juſticiary, againſt the perſons thereof accuſed, tho abſent, with all the Aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations libelled, or aggravating the ſaid Treaſon and Rebellion. The Lords Commiſſioners of Juſticiary, after conſideration of the ſaids Libels, and as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtricted in manner foreſaid, found the ſaid Libel ſo reſtricted, relevant, to infer the pains of Treaſon, and remitted the ſame to the knowledge of the Aſſiſe.</p>
            <p>And the Aſſiſe conſiſting of fifteen Perſons, being called and choſen out of the forty five Perſons that had been named and given out in a Liſt with the Libel and Criminal Letters, that the Defenders mtght ſee and object (if they had any Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt them) And no objection being moved againſt them, they were all lawfully ſworn.</p>
            <p>And then his Majeſty's Advocat produced for Probation the Letters above-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the Libel, directed by the Lords of his Majeſty's Privy Council againſt the ſaid Captain <hi>Simon Fraſer</hi> and his Complices, charging them to lay down their Arms, render up the houſes by them ſtuffed and fortified, and to ſubmit themſelves, and enter their perſons in Priſon, in the Tolbooth of <hi>Inverneſs,</hi> to underly and abide the Law, within the ſpace of Forty Eight Hours, under the pain of Treaſon and Rebellion, and denuncing them as ſuch to the Horn. And alſo (in caſe of their Diſobedience) commanding the Sheriff of
<hi>Inverneſs,</hi> and all other his Majeſty's Officers, and good Subjects, to riſe, concur, and act in<pb n="9" facs="tcp:188134:5"/>Arms in feir of War, for reducing the ſaid Rebels and Traitors to Obedience, and to apprehend and bring them to underly the Law, as the ſaids Letters more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bear, together with the Execution of the ſaids Letters, whereby it appeared, That the foreſaid Defenders were both lawfully charged upon the <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:leftblank"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>left blank</ex>
               </expan> day of <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:leftblank"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>left blank</ex>
               </expan> And for their Diſobedience and Contempt, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denunced, and put to the Horn upon the <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:leftblank"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>left blank</ex>
               </expan> day of the ſaid Month of <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:leftblank"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>left blank</ex>
               </expan> thereafter. And for the more Verification of the ſaid Charge and Execution, his Majeſty's Advocat did further adduce the Purſevant who execute the ſame, with the Witneſſes to the Executions, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all ſolemnly ſworn, made Faith upon the Truth thereof in all Points</p>
            <p>But here it is to be obſerved, That albeit the foreſaid Letters were directed by the Lords of his Majeſty's privy Council for charging the ſaids Defenders to lay down their Arms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And in caſe of their Diſobedience for denuncing them Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, and commanding the Sheriff of the Shire, and all others his Majeſty's Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, and good Subjects, to march againſt them as ſuch: And that the foreſaid Letters and Executions were alſo made uſe of by his Majeſties Advocat for a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Evidence of the Defenders Treaſonable riſing in Arms in open Rebellion, in regard of their obſtinate continuing in Arms after they were thereby charged; yet that the Defenders might have all fair Juſtice, and that no pretext might be left them to alledge, that it was incongruous and unjuſt to proceed to try them for their Crimes in Judgement, for adducing probation againſt them, when in the mean time they ſtood legally debarred, and were rendred incapable to compear, as having been denunced Fugitives, and ſo deprived of <hi>perſonam ſtandi in judicio,</hi> care was taken before the day appointed for their Compearance, to take out other Letters by Deliverance of his Majeſty's Council, for relaxing them from the Horn, and diſcharging their Out-Lawrie as Fugitives, that if they had plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to compear in Judgement, and defend, they might have done it as freely as any other of his Majeſty's Lieges; but the perſons inſiſted againſt, not compea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, his Majeſty's Advocat went on with his Probation. And the principal points to be proven conform to Interlocutor, being their treaſonable riſing in Arms, and open Rebellion againſt his Majeſty: He adduced in all Fourteen Witneſſes, whereof Eleven Men and three Women. The Men, <hi>Alexander Fraſer</hi> of <hi>Balnean, Thomas Fraſer</hi> of <hi>Gortilick, William Fraſer</hi> of <hi>Kilbokie, Robert Spence</hi> in <hi>Suddie, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander Mackinſh</hi> in <hi>Groom,</hi> Mr. <hi>Leonard Robertſon</hi> of
<hi>Stralock,</hi> Mr. <hi>George Fraſer,</hi> Sub-principal of the Colledge of <hi>Aberdeen, John Monro</hi> late Servitor to Captain <hi>Simon Fraſer, Alexander Stewart,</hi> Brother to <hi>Ulart, Peter Fraſer</hi> Servant to
<hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nean,</hi> and <hi>William Oig Fraſer</hi> Tenent to
<hi>Balnean.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who being all Witneſſes in this Caſe above Exception, and many of them Landed Men, did prove the Defenders their Treaſonable riſing in Arms, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Rebellion, with the greateſt Evidence that could be deſired. For tho it was not to be expected, that Eleven Witneſſes ſhould depone uniformly againſt Twenty Perſons, all engaged in a Treaſonable Combination, and riſing in Arms, conſiſting of ſeveral ſteps, Convocations, Rebellions, Meetings, Actings in a Tract of Time, and in ſeveral places; yet, it is moſt clear and Apparent from the Teſtimonies lying in Proceſs, and upon Record, That againſt every one of the Defenders, there were at leaſt two or three Witneſſes to prove their Acceſſion: And furder, That as to the Principal and moſt attrocious Acts of their Treaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Inſurrection, There was an evident Concurrence of the greateſt part of them all; In as much as the Witneſſes being ſolemnly ſworn, did make Faith, and give their Depoſitions upon the whole Points and Articles of both the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels,<pb n="10" facs="tcp:188134:6"/>in reference to all theſe particulars. Firſt, the Combination, Convocating, and conveening in Arms, without any lawful Authority. 2. The violent ſeiſing of the Priſoners. 3. The taking the Houſe of <hi>Fanellan,</hi> and keeping the Priſoners under Guards therein. 4. The keeping Gariſons and Guards upwards of a Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Men in the Houſe of <hi>Fanellan</hi> and <hi>Caſtledounie.</hi> 5. The raiſing of the Country by ſending the firie Croſs, and making the Cry called the <hi>Coronoch</hi> paſs thorow it, the ordinary ſignal for raiſing the Country in Arms in theſe parts. 6. The muſtering of men in Arms, under Commanders, and with Colours, ſometimes above Two Hundred, and ſometimes above Three Hundred. 7. The ſetting and keeping of Centinels and Guards, and detatching of Parties. 8. Their marching with their Priſoners under Armed Guards thorow the Country, to remote places. 9. And wherein, in effect the whole Defenders were engaged; Their continuing in Arms in feir of War, and an open hoſtile manner, ſometimes above two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, after they were charged in his Majeſty's Name, by warrant of the foreſaid Letters directed by the Lords of Privy Council, to lay down their Arms under the pain of Rebellion. And, 10. and laſtly, Their again convocating and conveening in Arms, ſeveral Months after they had been charged to lay down their Arms, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pain of Rebellion, as ſaid is, to the Number of Two or Three Hundred, and marching againſt, and again ſeiſing his Majeſty's free Lieges, for acting for his Majeſty's Authority, and making them Priſoners.</p>
            <p>All which particulars, the ſeveral and manifeſt ſteps of a moſt Treaſonable rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in Arms, and open Rebellion, having been proven, and for the greateſt and moſt attrocious part againſt the whole Defenders. The Probation as to the principal point was concluded with the moſt full and ſatisfying evidence.</p>
            <p>And as for the Aggravations, <hi>viz.</hi> The Injuries and Indignities done to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's free Lieges, and thoſe perſons of Honour and Quality, the making and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them as Priſoners with all ſeverity, the threatning them with Death, by ſetting up a Gallows in their View, before their Windows, when under cloſe Reſtraint in ſeveral Chambers, their carrying them about under Guards as Priſoners, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of them for ſeveral days, their moſt inhuman, cruel, and barbarous Uſage of the Lady Dowager of <hi>Lovat,</hi> and carrying her with them, in a moſt Afflicted captive Condition for ſeveral Weeks, thorow the moſt Barbarous and Mountain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous places that can be imagined, and extorting from her, by the Extremities of Violence, ſuch Writings and Declarations, as they were pleaſed to demand: All theſe Aggravations were alſo proven by the foreſaid Witneſſes, at leaſt two of them to every particular, of which the following Teſtimonies are a poſitive proof, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander Fraſer</hi> younger of <hi>Balnean,</hi> aged Twenty One years, examined, purged and ſworn, Depones, That he was preſent at <hi>Fanellan,</hi> when he ſaw the Lord <hi>Mungo Murray</hi> and the Lord
<hi>Saltoun</hi> brought Priſoners there, and made cloſe Priſoners there in ſeveral Rooms, with Centinels put on them, and that they were brought Priſoners there by Captain <hi>Simon Fraſer,</hi> and that when they came to <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nellan,</hi> a Houſe belonging to the Laird of <hi>Kinaries,</hi> the Doors were ſhut cloſe, and they forced them up, and put a Gariſon of armed Men in the Houſe. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pones, That he ſaw at <hi>Fanellan,</hi> about two or three days after the Lord <hi>Saltoun, &amp;c.</hi> was brought Priſoner, about two or three hundred Men in Arms under Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<hi>Fraſer's</hi> Command, and ſaw him muſter them there, and that they had Arms, ſuch as Guns, Swords, Piſtols, Targes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Depones, That about ſeven or eight days after the Lord <hi>Saltoun</hi> was made Priſoner, he was at <hi>Caſtledounie,</hi> where he ſee the Lady
<hi>Lovat,</hi> and that he ſaw a number of armed Men within the Houſe, and Centinels at the Gate, and that he ſaw Captain <hi>Simon Fraſer</hi> about the ſame time there. Depones, He ſaw Centinels ſitting on the Treſhold of my<pb n="11" facs="tcp:188134:6"/>Lady's Chamber Door, and that they continued there for a Night, after which time, the Deponent went away. Depones, He ſaw Parties ſent from <hi>Fanellan</hi> to <hi>Caſtledounie</hi> too and fro ſeveral times. Depones, That after the Lord <hi>Saltoun</hi> and Lord <hi>Mungo Murray</hi> were brought Priſoners to <hi>Fanellan,</hi> he ſaw a Gallows ſtanding before the Windows, where the ſaids two Lords were keeped cloſs Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, which was not there the day they were brought Priſoners. Depones, That a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout nine or ten days after the Lord <hi>Saltoun</hi> and the Lord <hi>Mungo Murray</hi> were taken Priſoners, he did ſee one Night at
<hi>Caſtledounie,</hi> Captain <hi>Simon Fraſer</hi> and Mr. <hi>Robert Monro</hi> the Miniſter at <hi>Caſtledounie,</hi> and being deſired by Captain <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard Robertſon</hi> of <hi>Straloch,</hi> to get him notice of my Lady's Condition, he went to my Lady's Chamber Door, and heard her Sighing and Moaning, and it was then about the Reik of Day, and that he heard the Pipes playing in the Dining Room next to my Lady's Chamber. The ſame Night he ſaw my Lady's two Women in another Room, with Centinels ſet upon them, and the two Women Weeping, and this was about Midnight he ſaw them. And this is the Truth, as he ſhall Anſwer to GOD. <hi>Sic Subſcribitur,</hi> Al. Fraſer. <hi>Lothian,</hi> I. P. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Fraſer</hi> of <hi>Gortulig,</hi> aged Thirty Years, Married, Purged and Sworn, Depones, That about the beginning of
<hi>October,</hi> Captain <hi>Simon Fraſer</hi> and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent coming from
<hi>Inverneſs,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Saltoun</hi> and the Lord <hi>Mungo Murray</hi> from <hi>Caſtledounie,</hi> there having met them in the Wood of
<hi>Moncreive</hi> ſome Armed Men, when they were met together, they did make up Thirty or Fourty Foot, beſide Horſes, all in Arms, where the Lord
<hi>Saltoun</hi> and Lord <hi>Mungo</hi> being Rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing peaceably, Captain
<hi>Simon</hi> gave Orders to his Company, to take my Lord <hi>Saltoun</hi> either Dead or Alive, and accordingly came up cloſs to my Lord
<hi>Saltoun</hi> and Lord <hi>Mungo,</hi> and aſſaulted them with Bended Piſtols, and commanded them to render themſelves Priſoners, My Lord
<hi>Saltoun</hi> asking for what cauſe, he An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, becauſe it was his Pleaſure: And the Deponent did ſee Captain <hi>Simon,</hi> and his Party, Diſmounting and Diſarming the Lord <hi>Saltoun</hi> and Lord
<hi>Mungo,</hi> and all that were with them, and threatning them, the Foot having Guns pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented and Durks drawn, and the Horſemens Piſtols cocked, and thereafter they were ſet on Countrey Horſe in ſtead of their own, with Guards in Arms ſurroun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them, and carried them in that Poſture to
<hi>Fanellan,</hi> where they were made cloſs Priſoners in ſeveral Rooms, and Centinels put upon the Rooms, and a Guard keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Houſe, where they ſtay'd four or five Nights. Depones, That immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly thereafter, he heard the Firie Croſs was ſent through the Countrey, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veen the Men, and accordingly the next Night, there conveened at <hi>Fanellan</hi> about three or four hundred Men with Guns, Swords and Piſtols, and Pipers: And De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pones, That they were all commanded by Captain <hi>Simon,</hi> and under him, by their ſeveral Under-Leaders. Depones, That there was a conſiderable Party ſent from <hi>Fanellan,</hi> to my Lady <hi>Lovats</hi> Houſe at
<hi>Caſtledounie,</hi> and that Parties were from time to time relieved, and that there were Centinels put upon ſeveral Rooms of the Houſe, and particularly upon my Lady's Chamber, and that he ſaw Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Simon</hi> there, and that he was the Perſon that gave the Orders. Depones, That he ſaw the Lord <hi>Saltoun</hi> and Lord <hi>Mungo</hi> carried priſoners to the Iſle of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies,</hi> where they were keeped Priſoners with a Guard of Fifty or Sixty Men in Arms. And this is the Truth, as he ſhall Anſwer to GOD. <hi>Sic Subſcribitur</hi> T. Fraſer. <hi>Lothian,</hi> I. P. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Fraſer</hi> of <hi>Kilbokie,</hi> Aged Fourty Years, Married, Purged and Sworn, Depones, That in <hi>October</hi> laſt, the Deponent came to the Houſe of <hi>Fanellan,</hi> where Captain <hi>Simon</hi> was with two or three hundred Men all Armed, who had<pb n="12" facs="tcp:188134:7"/>conveened there upon a Firie Croſs, which was ſent by Captain
<hi>Simon</hi>'s Order through the Countrey, and it was the third day after the Lord <hi>Saltoun</hi> and Lord <hi>Mungo</hi> were taken Priſoners: And the Deponent ſaw them there, and Guards and Centinels upon them as Priſoners; And likeways ſaw a Gallows erected over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Windows of their Chambers: And the Deponent having asked at Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Simon,</hi> what that mean'd, he Anſwered, That it was to terrifie the Lord <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toun</hi> and Lord <hi>Mungo.</hi> Depones, That he was preſent when the ſaids Lords were carried Priſoners from <hi>Fanellan</hi> to the Iſle of <hi>Egies,</hi> where they were detained Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners by the ſaid Captain <hi>Simon</hi>'s Command. Depones, That before the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent went firſt to <hi>Fanellan,</hi> he was at <hi>Caſtledounie</hi> my Lady <hi>Lovats</hi> Dwelling, where there was a Party of upwards of three or fourſcore of Armed Men, and ſaw them keeping Guard at the Gates, and Captain <hi>Simon</hi> was there, and gave them Orders as Commander.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert Spence</hi> in <hi>Suddie,</hi> Aged Twenty Four Years, Married, Purged and Sworn, Depones, That Captain <hi>Simon Fraſer</hi> having carried my Lady <hi>Lovat</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longſt with him from <hi>Kirkhill,</hi> and having heard, that there was a Party of Red-Coats, with Lord <hi>James Murray</hi> and ſome Gentlemen, coming to reſcue my Lady, Captain
<hi>Simon</hi> did ſend word through the Countrey, to raiſe the Firie Croſs, to warn the Countrey to come for their Defence. Depones, That when my La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy left Captain <hi>Simon,</hi> there would have been about two or three hundred Men in Arms with him. And this is the Truth, as he ſhall Anſwer to God. <hi>Sic Subſcribitur,</hi> Robert Spence. <hi>Ad. Cockburn,</hi> I. P. D.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>George Fraſer</hi> Sub-Principal of the Colledge of
<hi>Aberdeen,</hi> Purged and Sworn, Depones, That when my Lord
<hi>Saltoun,</hi> Lord <hi>Mungo Murray,</hi> and others were made Priſoners the time libelled, he was one of the Company, and that Captain <hi>Simon</hi> commanded the Party that apprehended them, which conſiſted or Fourteen Horſe and Fifty Foot, or thereby, all armed with Swords, Piſtols and Guns; and one of them called <hi>Hutcheon Oig</hi> came up with a Bended Piſtol on my Lord <hi>Saltoun,</hi> and deſired them to render, and diſmounted them, and put them on little Horſes, and carried them Priſoners to
<hi>Fanellan,</hi> and keeped them there Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners under Guards by the ſpace of ſix days, and that there was a Gallows put up, and there was a Convocation of Men in Arms, ſometimes to the number of three or four hundred Men in Arms, with Colours diſplayed and Pipers playing. And this is the Truth, as he ſhall Anſwer to GOD. <hi>Sic Subſcribitur,</hi> Geo. Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet. <hi>Lothian,</hi> I. P. D.</p>
            <p>And further, the Deteſtable and Horrid Violence done to the Lady Dowager by Captain <hi>Simon Fraſer,</hi> and his wicked Complices, was yet more particularly and diſtinctly proven by Mr. <hi>Leanord Robertſon</hi> of <hi>Straloch,</hi> and three Women, who no doubt, in a caſe ſo Circumſtantiat, were not only neceſſary, but moſt lawful ſufficient Witneſſes. But becauſe this Violence was acted and perpetrat by the ſaid Captain <hi>Simon,</hi> with ſuch Cruelty and Barbarity, as is ſcarce Credible, the ſumm of the Evidence given in this Matter, is here more particularly ſet down as follows.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Leonard Robertſon</hi> of <hi>Straloch,</hi> Aged 44.
<hi>ſolutus,</hi> purged and Sworn, Depones That upon the ſixteenth of
<hi>October</hi> laſt, being <hi>Saturday,</hi> he came to
<hi>Inverneſs,</hi> and was there informed, that the Lady Dowager of
<hi>Lovat</hi> was under Reſtraint at <hi>Caſtledouni,</hi> whereupon he repaired to that place, and after ſome difficulty made, got Acceſs to my Lady, who acquainted him with the Propoſals that Captain <hi>Simon Fraſer</hi> had made to her; and intreated the Deponent to perſwade the Lord <hi>Saltoun,</hi> and her Brother Lord <hi>James Murray,</hi> to condeſcend to the Terms;<pb n="13" facs="tcp:188134:7"/>which the Deponent undertook: And having returned to <hi>Inverneſs,</hi> prevailed with them to ſign the Articles, for her own, and Lord <hi>Mungo</hi>'s Liberation, and brought them back to <hi>Caſtledounie</hi> on <hi>Tueſday,</hi> to get my Ladies hand to them. Which being done, the Deponent expected nothing, but that my Lady was fully at liberty. But when he was conveying her to her Horſe, they were both ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped at my Lady's Chamber Door, and there was a Chair and a Centry ſet at my Lady's Door, and all the reſt of the Centries doubled; and the Deponent him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, after ſome time, was put under a Guard of Centinels, and was ſo detained under Reſtraint, till the next day at ten of the Clock; That complaining to Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Simon,</hi> the Deponent was permitted to pay a Viſit to my Lady, whom he ſaw in a very diſconſolat Condition, and ſoftly ſpoken in his Ear, <hi>For Chriſts ſake take me out of this place either dead or alive,</hi> and that he obſerved my Ladies Face all ſwollen, and ſhe fell in a Sownd the time the Deponent was with her; and the Lady ſuſpecting that he had not fully heard what ſhe had ſpoken to him, ſent her Servant Mrs. <hi>Mackbryar</hi> with Commiſſion to repeat the ſame words to him, which ſhe did. And the Deponent thinks Captain
<hi>Simon</hi> had at leaſt Three Hundred Men with him at that time, all well armed, in, and about the Houſe of <hi>Caſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounie,</hi> and that he heard at the time ſome perſon lamenting, and the Bag-pipe played about the ſame time, but knows not whether it was to drown the Voice, or not. And furder depones, That the next time he ſaw my Lady, was, That the Laird of
<hi>Collodine,</hi> and the Deponent came to the Water ſide, near the Iſle of <hi>Ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis;</hi> and Captain <hi>Simon</hi> having come over to them by Boat, the Deponent deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſee my Lady, which he ſhun'd, telling him, That my Lady did not deſire to ſee him; and the Deponent replyed, That it was not done like a Comerad; eſpecially ſeing it was reported at
<hi>Inverneſs,</hi> That my Lady was dead, or near ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piring. Captain
<hi>Simon</hi> anſwered, That he ſhould be ſoon cleared of the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and returning in his Boat, he cauſed bring out my Lady in their ſight: But ſo weak, as ſhe was ſupported by two, and then carried her back again to a little Houſe upon that Iſland: But the Deponent having asked at Mrs.
<hi>Mackbryar</hi> from the other ſide of the Water, to try at her Lady, if ſhe had diſcharged the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to ſee her; ſhe went accordingly, and brought back word, That ſhe deſired nothing more than to ſee the Deponent, except her own Liberation, and to tell her Brother Lord
<hi>James,</hi> that ſhe was ſome better, and lived longer than ſhe deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; And that the Deponent ſaw my Lady ſeveral times after that, where ſhe made heavie Complaints of the bad and rude uſage ſhe had met with; but her Guards, and others ſuſpecting the Deponent, becauſe he would not comply anent ſome Papers, they were drawing up for their own pretended Security, he had not that free converſe which he had formerly; and that this was the third or fourth Night after the Charge given them by the Herauld, to diſſipat and lay down their Arms, and ſet my Lady at liberty. And at the time when my Lady parted with them, and went away with my Lord
<hi>Forbes,</hi> the Deponent ſaw about two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Men in Arms with Captain
<hi>Simon Fraſer. Sic Subſcribitur</hi> Leonard Robertſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Amilie Rioch,</hi> late Servitrix to Lady <hi>Lovat,</hi> aged
16 years, ſworn and purged, depones, That about the time libelled, ſhe being a Servant to my Lady, Captain <hi>Simon Fraſer,</hi> with ſeveral Armed Men, came to <hi>Caſtledounie,</hi> and ſet Centinels on my Lady's Chamber without, and within the Doors, with drawn Swords; That Captain
<hi>Simons</hi> Men carried by force my Lady's waiting Maids, Mrs.
<hi>Mackbryar,</hi> Mrs. <hi>Janet Fraſer,</hi> and the Deponent out of her Room, and made them Priſoners in another Room, That about two of the Clock in the Morning, two armed<pb n="14" facs="tcp:188134:8"/>Men came, and carried the Deponent back to the Lady's Chamber, where ſhe did ſee the Lady ſitting on the Ground, her Hair hanging down about her Head, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning backward upon the Bed-ſtock; That one <hi>Donald Beaton</hi> was pulling off my Lady's Shoes, and Captain <hi>Simon</hi> was holding Aquavitae and burnt Feathers to her Noſe, becauſe ſhe was then in a ſwarf; that thereafter they commanding the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent to take off my Lady's Shoes, and when ſhe offered ſo to do, my Lady ſpurned her away with her feet, ſhewing her unwillingneſs; That the Deponent refuſing to take off her Cloaths, Captain <hi>Simon</hi> ordered to beat her; that <hi>Fraſer</hi> of <hi>Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monavie</hi> did then hold up the Lady in his Arms, and Captain <hi>Simon</hi> pulled off her Petticoats, and ſought a Knife from <hi>Hugh Monro</hi> to cut her Stays; and becauſe he had none, the Captain ordered <hi>Fraſer</hi> of <hi>Kinmonavie</hi> to cutt her Stays with his Durk; and then they threw the Lady upon the Bed: But the Deponent ſaying that ſhe would take off the Lady's Stays, they went a little out of the Room, in which time the Deponent did again faſten the Stays; but they returning, were diſpleaſed, that the Stays were not take off, and commanded to put the Deponent out of the Room; and then they turned the Lady upon her Face, and ſtretched out her Arms, and ſo took off her Stays, which the Deponent did ſee, becauſe ſhe went not out of the Room, but ſtood at the foot of the Bed. And when the Deponent was going away, ſhe heard my Lady cry, but the Bag-pipe did play all the time in the next Room to my Lady's Chamber, that her Cries might not be heard. Depones, That next Morning ſhe went in to the Lady's Chamber, and ſee her head hang o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Bed, and nothing upon it, except a Handkerchief; the Deponent did ſee all the Lady's Face ſwollen, and ſhe ſpoke nothing, but gave her a broad look. And the Deponent thought that my Lady was not ſenſible for a day or two thereafter; for ſhe did not know Lord <hi>Mungo</hi> her Brother the next Morning, when he came to ſee her, and when her Servant told her, here is your Brother at the Bed ſide, the Lady asked, what Brother, albeit ſhe was looking him in the Face with fair Day-light. Depones, That when ſhe and the other Servants were carried by force the firſt Night, out of my Lady's Chamber; the Lady ſtood up, and held out her Arms, and cryed: And when
<hi>Dumballocks</hi> Lady came the next Morning to the Room, and called her Madam; my Lady anſwered. <hi>Call me not Madam, but the moſt miſerable wretch alive.</hi> Depones, That ſhe ſee my Lady carried priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner from
<hi>Caſtledounie</hi> to the Iſle of <hi>Aigis</hi> at twelve of the Clock at Night, and from that to <hi>Culgrain,</hi> and from that to <hi>Deanie,</hi> and then to the Iſle of <hi>Matlie.</hi> The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of her Knowledge, becauſe ſhe went along with her.</p>
            <p>This Depoſition was the more credited, That the Maid, tho young, not above ſixteen years, did nevertheleſs, in the preſence of the Court, and Hundreds atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it, depone with a firmneſs and conſtancy, particulary obſerved by all that heard her, and her foreſaid Depoſition was immediatly confirmed by <hi>Janet Fraſer,</hi> Daughter to
<hi>Dumballoch,</hi> who agreed in her Depoſition with <hi>Amilie Reoch,</hi> as to the Violence put upon the Lady, and her being carried forcibly from her, and as to the ſad and afflicted Condition, wherein ſhe ſee her the next day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Janet Fraſer,</hi> Daughter to <hi>Dumballoch,</hi> aged 16 years, unmarried, ſworn and purged, depones, That at the time libelled, Captain <hi>Simon Fraſer,</hi> and ſeveral armed Men, came to the Houſe of <hi>Caſtledounie;</hi> and thereafter there being Guards and Centries ſet on my Lady's Chamber-door, the Deponent and Mrs. <hi>Mackbryar</hi> being my Lady <hi>Lovats</hi> Servants, were about Twelve of the Clock at Night, carried by force out of my Lady's Chamber, and my Lady taking hold of the Deponents Cloaths, and crying out when the Deponent was pulled away
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:188134:8"/>by Force, my Lady fell on her Face. Depones, That next Morning the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent came to my Lady's Chamber, about Eight a Clock in the Morning, and did ſee my Lady's Head hanging over the Bed-Stock, and ſee her Face ſwollen. And the Deponent enquiring anent my Lady's Health, my Lady anſwered, <hi>I am Dead.</hi> And about Twelve a Clock that day, my Lady appeared altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible, and did take the Deponent for Lady
<hi>Catharine</hi> my Lady's Siſter, who had died ſeveral Years before, and about Four a Clock the ſame Afternoon, my Lady did not know her Brother my Lord <hi>Mungo,</hi> and could not ſpeak to him. Depones, that about Two a Clock the ſame day, my Lady fell in a Swerf and continued out and in the Swerf about two Hours. And this is the Truth, as ſhe ſhall anſwer to God. And Depones ſhe cannot Write.</p>
            <p>Likeas <hi>Chriſtian Macklain,</hi> late Servitrix to <hi>James Fraſer</hi> of <hi>Relict,</hi> did likewiſe in her Depoſition agree with them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtian Macklain,</hi> late Servitrix to <hi>James Fraſer</hi> of <hi>Relict,</hi> Aged 24 Years, un-married, Purged, and Sworn, and Interrogat by the <hi>Aberuchil,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Thomas Fraſer</hi> Sworn Interpreter, in reſpect ſhe cannot Speak the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, Depones, That the time Lybelled, particularly that Night that they talk of the pretended ſham Marriage, ſhe being a Servant in the Family, had the Charge of a young Child, being in the next Room to my Lady's, and the Door of my Lady's Room, and the Room where the Deponent was being open, and the Doors Guarded by Armed Men, ſhe heard my Lady Moan and Lament: In the mean there were Bag-pipes playing, and yet ſhe heard my Ladies Voice ſo loud, that the Sound of the Bag-pipe did not drown her Voice. Depones, That ſhe ſaw <hi>Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monavie</hi> drawing a Durk from one of the Centries that was at the Room where the Deponent was, and ruſh into the Room where the Lady was with it. Depones, That the Deponent was Guarded ſo ſtrictly, that ſhe could get neither Meat nor Drink for her ſelf nor the Child, nor none allowed to come near her from Twelve a Clock of the Day, to Eight a Clock next Morning. Depones, ſhe ſaw Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Simon Fraſer</hi> there, with the moſt part of the other Perſons inſiſted againſt, all in Arms, and ſaw a great many moe People in Arms, in and about the Houſe. Further Depones, That before the Pipes were bended up, ſhe heard my Lady cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and clap her hands, ſaying, <hi>Is there no Perſon that hath any Chriſtian Blood in them, who will have no reſpect to my Woes,</hi> and repeated very often,
<hi>Lord have Mercy on her Soul.</hi> This is the Truth, as ſhe ſhall Anſwer to GOD. And Depones ſhe cannot Write. <hi>Sic Subſcribitur,</hi> Thomas Fraſer.</p>
            <p>All which Depoſitions, as to the Centries ſet within, and without the Lady's Chamber, and the Violence then done her, and the playing of the Bag-Pipe to ſuppreſs her Cryes, and the carrying of her Captive from Place, to Place, were further confirmed by what the foreſaid Men Witneſſes did Declare in their ſeveral Depoſitions as to theſe Points.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty's Advocat did alſo produce, and lay before the Aſſiſe, the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Letters mentioned in the firſt Libel, Write by
<hi>Beaufort</hi> Elder and Younger and their Complices, for Declaring their wicked Conſpiracy and Combination, and which Letter was alſo Atteſted by ſeveral of the Witneſſes.</p>
            <p>From all which it is moſt manifeſt, That the Defenders their Treaſonable Riſing in Arms and open Rebellion againſt his Majeſty, and the Aggravations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove-libelled, were fully and clearly Proven: And accordingly the Aſſiſe did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn their Verdict, bearing, That they all in one Voice did find the Libel, with the Aggravations thereof, as the ſame was reſtricted by the Interlocutor of the<pb n="16" facs="tcp:188134:9"/>Lords, clearly proven againſt the ſaid Captain <hi>Simon Fraſer,</hi> and the other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons inſiſted againſt in abſence, as ſaid is.</p>
            <p>After opening and reading of which Verdict of Aſſiſe, the Lords Juſtice Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, Juſtice Clerk, and Commiſſioners of Juſticiary, in reſpect thereof, Decerned and Adjudged the ſaid Captain
<hi>Simon Fraſer,</hi> and the whole Perſons contained in the above-written Verdict, to be Execute to the Death, Demeaned as Traitors, and to undergo the Pains of Treaſon, and utter Puniſhment, appointed by the Laws of the Realm, at ſuch Times and Places, and in ſuch Manner, as the ſaids Lords ſhould appoint: And ordain their Name, Fame, Memory and Honours to be extinct, and their Arms to be riven forth, and delete out of the Books of Arms; ſo that their Poſterity may never have Place, nor be able hereafter to Bruik or Joice any Honours, Offices, Titles, or Dignities, within the Realm in time coming: And to have Forfeited, Amitted, and Tint, all and ſundry their Lands, Heretages, Tacks, Steedings, Rooms, Poſſeſſions, Goods and Gear whatſoever pertaining to them, to our Sovereign Lord, to remain perpetually with his Majeſty in Property. And this Sentence was by Sound of Trumpet, and all other Solemnities, given for Doom.</p>
            <p>For Concluſion then of this Account, it remains only to be remarked. <hi>Firſt,</hi> That both the Lybels are ſo evidently relevant, and the Probation ſo full and clear, that there cannot remain the leaſt Scruple or Doubt, as to the orderly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedure, and juſt Iſſue of this Tryal.</p>
            <p>It may poſſibly occur, that all the foreſaid Convocations, Meetings and Actings in Arms, were only upon the Occaſion of a pretended privat Quarrel, and not deſigned againſt His Majeſty and his Government. And further, that the foreſaids Perſons found guilty, did ſeveral times openly declare, That from all their Bonds and Engagements to maintain and ſtand by one another, the King was expreſly excepted. But to this it may be Anſwered, that the Duty and Crimes of Subjects are to be meaſured and judged by Deeds, and not by Words. That the Words of the Law are moſt expreſs, And it ſhall be high Treaſon to the Subjects of this Kingdom, or any Number of them, more or leſs, upon any Ground or Pretext whatſoever, to riſe and continue in Arms, to maintain Forts or Gariſons, to make Peace or War, to make Treaties and Leagues with Foreigners, or amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, without his Majeſty's ſpecial Authority and Approbation firſt interponed thereto. That there is nothing more eaſy and ordinary for Men, than to colour their Treaſonable Riſing in Arms, with ſpecious Pretences and Excuſes. And <hi>Laſtly,</hi> That it is moſt certain, That as the foreſaid Criminals, and their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices, did diſobey and contemn His Majeſty's Authority, charging them to lay down their Arms under the Pain of Rebellion, ſo had they been able to have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and overthrown the whole Forces and Strength of the Government, they had certainly done it, in the Proſecution of their Wicked Deſigns.</p>
            <p>It may likewiſe appear ſtrange to ſome, to hear and ſee ſo many Forefeited up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Occaſion. But theſe Perſons ought firſt to conſider, that the Perſons found guilty, were the Chief Ring-leaders in all the Steps of the foreſaid Rebellion, and Barbarous Outrages, and who forced others to take Arms.</p>
            <p>As alſo they ought to reflect, that ſeveral Hundreds whom the Law reaches, are nevertheleſs paſt by and over-look'd, and the foreſaid Perſons only inſiſted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, as neceſſary Examples to reſtrain ſuch Lawleſs and Pernicious Practices; And that tho the foreſaid twenty Perſons be condemned, for the Indiſpenſible Maintaining of His Majeſty's juſt Authority, and Repreſſing and Curbing the Madneſs of ſuch Heady Deſperat Traitors: Yet the Eſtate and intereſt of all of them<pb n="17" facs="tcp:188134:9"/>taken complexly, are not worth Fifty Pound
<hi>Sterling</hi> by Year; nor are they in the leaſt valuable as to the Peace of the Kingdom, it being known, that the greateſt part of them were Thieves and Murderers, and ſo glad of any pretence to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue their Lawleſs Practices, and keep themſelves out of the Hands of Juſtice.</p>
            <p>Some few Moneths after the foreſaid Tryal, the ſaids <hi>Hugh Fraſer</hi> alias <hi>Hut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheon Oig,</hi> and <hi>John Fraſer</hi> younger of <hi>Migavie,</hi> two of the Convict Perſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove-named, being apprehended in the North, were ſent Priſoners, under a Guard of his Majeſty's Forces, to the Tolbooth of <hi>Edinburgh:</hi> And being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon the 11th of <hi>April</hi> laſt before the Lords of Juſticiary, and Interrogat, if they did bear the Names and Deſignations above-written, and if they knew any others of theſe names and Deſignations, they acknowledged their Names to be as above, <hi>viz. Hugh Fraſer,</hi> alias <hi>Hutcheon Oig,</hi> and <hi>John Fraſer</hi> younger of <hi>Migavie,</hi> and that they knew of no other Perſons of their Names and Deſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which judicial Acknowledgment they Signed.</p>
            <p>The ſaid <hi>Hugh Fraſer,</hi> alias <hi>Hutcheon Oig,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>John Fraſer</hi> younger of <hi>Migavie,</hi> by the former Sentence, being ordained to undergo the Pains of Treaſon, appointed by the Laws of this Kingdom, at ſuch Times, Places, and in ſuch Manner, as the Lords of Juſticiary ſhould appoint, in reſpect they were then abſent: And they being now brought before the Lords, to hear the time, Place, and Manner of the Execution appointed, the Lords of Juſticiary Decer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and adjudged the ſaid <hi>Hugh</hi> and <hi>John Fraſers</hi> to be taken to the Croſs of <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> upon the fourth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> thereafter, betwixt two and four a Clock in the Afternoon, and there to have their Heads ſevered from their Bodies.</p>
            <p>It being certain, that there is a Remiſſion under his Majeſty's Royal Hand, which is appointed to paſs the great Seal <hi>per Saltum:</hi> It is thought neceſary to publiſh ſome Paragraphs of two of his Letters, containing dangerous Inſinuations againſt his Majeſty, and moſt Villainous Expreſſions concerning the late Queen of Bleſſed Memory, for ſatisfying all his Majeſty's loving Subjects, how unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the ſaid Captain <hi>Fraſer</hi> is of his Majeſty's Pardon; The true Copy of the ſaids Paragraphs, whereof the Principals are ready to be produced, is hereto ſubjoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Beaufort</hi>
                        <date>12 <hi>January</hi> 1695.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>Tell Sir <hi>Robert,</hi> That I hope he'll pledge me a Bumper that I am drinking to Q. M. Dredgie.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Sic ſubſcribitur,</hi> Sim. Frazer.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>Direct to <hi>Thomas Frazer.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>A Paragraph of another Letter.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Beaufort</hi>
                        <date>12 <hi>January</hi> 1695.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I doubt not you will be in mourning for Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> but I am reſolved to buy none till K. <hi>W.</hi> die, which perhaps may ſerve for the next Summer Sure; and I hope you will give me a Hat and Gloves for it.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Sic ſubſcribitur,</hi> Simon Frazer.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
